Notes 04/09/2019
Internal verification: using type information to force type checker to maintain qualities about the code

Static scope:
-Local variables have a statically determinable scope where they are valid
Dynamic scope: scope of variables cannot be determined from the code- can reference variables that are local to a function
Scope: place in program where can refer to variable
Eg: 
let X = (let x = 3+3 in x+3 ) in X+4
Example, (let x = 3+3 in ) let X = x + 3 in X + 4
Sigma Types- generalize pairs
Eg: Non-zero natural number
Σ 
N x (iszero n = ff)
HW egample

tpCheck : RawExpr → maybe (Σ Tp (λ T → Expr T))
Take a raw expression, turns it into a type and a typed version of that type
Σ  ℕ (λ n → iszero n ≡ ff )
f: inputs → preconditons →  Σ output (lambda output → postconditions)

Example:
let expression
let _string_ = expression1 in expression2
Var : string → raw expression

Garbage collection
-Automatically reclaim memory no longer being used (Part of runtime system)
	->Take burden off programmer
		C/C++ do not provide automatic garbage collection, lead to memory errors
-Runtime system permits program to access memory, operating system stops processes from accessing memory not allocated for them
-Memory Errors can occur when two parts of a program are given the same memory space, which leads to them corrupting eachother's data
-Have to tell runtime system when done with memory, if tells runtime too early, can also cause corruption of data
	->Memory errors are extremely difficult to fix, as it's totally unclear which process is using the memory
-Last error can occur when program gives memory but then forgets to free memory
-Garbage collection won't help if reference to datastructure is maintained after it is used

GC is impossible for all program but for 3 assumtions is possible
1. GC has access to program's reference graph (nodes = allocated chunks of memory, edge from n1 to n2 if n1 references n2 [program can use information from n1 to access n2])
	-In Haskell, this is possible because every variable is created by constructors
	-C/C++ allow you to access memory at arbitrary locations, so reference graph cannot be known
	Garbage memory-> dead memory, unreachable from program's current reference graph's roots
	Roots: Running program's current direct access points to reference graph (In-scope variables)

Algorithms to implement garbage collection
-Reference counting
-Mark and sweep
-Copying collection
-Hybrids

Reference Counting
-Count how many incoming references there are to a cell
-When you add a reference to cell, increment its ref count, when dropping a reference, decrement its refcount
-When refcount == 0, reclaim node, decrement the nodes it references
-Doesn't need too much memory- most variables don't have that many incoming pointers!
If object has more than max ref count, treat object as immortal
-Bounded pause times
	-recyling refcount - cells is constant time operation
	-Good for real-time applications
-Won't recycle live memory
Negatives:
	-Extra memory traffic for updating ref counts
	-Not complete- may miss some dead memory (Node references itself, circular set)
Mark and Sweep
-Run through the roots, mark every cell as you go going from the root
-If a cell is unmarked after this, it can be recycled
-If cell is marked, unmark it and continue
Pros:
-Sound and complete, niether collects live memory nor leaves any dead memory
Cons:
-Expensive: Have to traverse entire reference graph, and all dead memory as well
	-Cache is cleared out
	-Unbounded pause time, stops the entire program while garbage collection algorithm is running
Optimization for mark phase: 
	-Pointer-reversing traversal: during marking phase, have to allocate memory to make recursive calls
	-Maintain Two pointers- Where you came from, and where to go next
	-When you're about to go to the next node, reverse the current node's pointer to point to where you came from
Copying Collection
-Mark current memory as from, other part of memory as to
-Traverse ref graph, in from from space, copying to the front of the of To space
-Update global and local variables, to refer to To space
-Switch From and to spaces
Pros: sound and complete (only traverse the live memory), automatically defragments memory, good for hybrids
Cons- takes up half the memory